阿尔法小分队荣誉译制
翻：@Auriance校：@ErrorEnvyEnchant 压制：@Mihael_Ho
长期招募 详情见微博置顶@阿尔法小分队科教组
大家好 我是凯莉·安 欢迎来到计算机速成课
Hi, I'm Carrie Anne and welcome to Crash Course Computer Science.
之前几期我们探讨了计算机工作的原理
Over the last few episodes, We've talked a lot about the mechanics of how computers work,
复杂电路如何存取内存数据
how they use complex circuits to save and retrieve values from memory,
以及如何使用数据完成计算 比如两数相加
and perform operations on those values, like adding two numbers together.
我们还简要提到了计算机程序
We've even briefly talked about sequences of operations, which is a computer program.
但我们还没说明计算机如何加载程序
What we haven't talked about is how a program gets into a computer.
记得吗 第7和第8期讲过
You might remember in episode 7 and 8 ,
当我们在当时制造的CPU步进简单的示例程序
when we stepped through some simple example programs for the CPU that we had created.
为了简化
For simplicity, we just waved our hands
我们直接假设程序已经在内存里了
and said that the program was already magically in memory.
但实际上 程序必须要经过加载
But in reality, programs have to be loaded into a computer's memory.
这不是魔术 这是计算机科学
It's not magic. It's computer science.
对机器编程的需求远早于计算机的出现
The need to programme machines existed way before the development of computers.
纺织业是一个典型的例子
The most famous example of this was in textile manufacturing.
如果需要一张大的红桌布
If you just wanted to weave a big red tablecloth,
只需要让织布机带着红纺线编织就行了
you could simply feed red thread into a loom and let it run.
但如果想要布匹带有条纹或者格子的花纹呢
But what about if you wanted the cloth to have a pattern like stripes or plaid?
工人就必须不断按照花纹的样式调整织布机
Workers would have to periodically reconfigure the loom as dictated by the pattern,
但这样非常耗费人力 所以当时有花纹的织物很贵
but this was labor intensive which made patterned fabrics expensive.
约瑟夫·玛丽·雅卡尔发明的可编程织布机应运而生
In response, Joseph Marie Jacquard developed a programmable textile loom,
【注：约瑟夫·玛丽·雅卡尔（1752年6月7日－1834年8月7日），法国发明家。
1. 因为发明雅卡尔织布机，在1805年受拿破仑皇帝嘉奖3000法郎终生养老金(按黄金
比价，相当于2018年人民币23万5千元)
2. 在随后的6年，每台出售的织布机，他可以抽得专利费50法郎(同上，约人民币4千元)】
它于1801年面世
which he first demonstrated in 1801.
布匹每行的花纹由打孔卡确定
The pattern for each row of the cloth was defined by a punched card.
孔的有无
The presence or absence of a hole in the card
影响经纱在织布机中的高低
determined if a specific thread was held high or low in the loom.
【注：经纱与纬纱互相垂直，二者互相交织成为织物】
这样 称为纬纱的横向纺线得以从经纱的上或下通过
Such that the cross thread called the weft passed above or below the thread.
为了让每行的花纹不同 打孔卡被连成了长串
To vary the pattern across rows these punch cards were arranged in long chains,
对织布机来说 这就是连续的指令
forming a sequence of commands for the loom.
有点耳熟吧
Sound familiar?
很多人认为雅卡尔的织布机是最早的编程形式之一
Many consider Jacquard's loom to be one of the earliest forms of programming.
打孔卡也成为了低成本 可靠并且相对可读的数据存储介质
Punched cards, turned out to be a cheap , reliable, fairly human readable way to store data.
雅卡尔织布机发明大约100年后 1890年人口普查也用到了打孔卡
Nearly a century later, punch cards were use to help tabulate the 1890 newest census
第1期讲过的
which we talked about in episode 1.
每张卡存储了一个人的信息
Each card held an individual person's data.
比如 种族 婚姻状况 孩子数量 出生地等等
Things like race, marital status, number of children, country of birth, and so on.
对于普查的每个问题
For each demographic question,
工作人员都会在对应答案的位置打孔
a census worker would punch out a hole of the appropriate position.
当把卡片插入编表机时
When a card was fed into the tabulating machine,
卡片上的孔会让其对应结果的总数加1
a hole would cause the running total for that specific answer to be increased by one.
这样可以输入整个国家民众的数据
In this way you could feed the entire county's worth of people
并最终得到所有普查问题的结果
and at the end you'd have running totals for all of the questions that you asked.
需要指出一点 早期的编表机并不是计算机
It is important to note here that early tabulating machines were not truly computers
因为它只能完成一样工作——汇总数据
as they can only do one thing-tabulate.
所有的操作都是固定不变的
Their operation was fixed and not programmable.
打孔卡仅仅记录数据而不是程序
Punch cards stored data, but not a program.
在其后的60年 这些机器的性能不断提升
Over the next 60 years, these business machines grew in capability,
实现了减法 乘法 除法
adding features to subtract, multiply, divide,
甚至能够完成何时执行某个特定操作的简单决策
and even make simple decisions about when to perform certain operations.
为了能触发能够完成计算的恰当功能
To trigger these functions appropriately, so that different calculations could be performed,
程序员发明了控制台
a programmer accessed a control panel.
面板上排满了小插孔
This panel was full of little sockets,
程序员可以将电缆插入孔中
into which a programmer would plug cables to pass values and signals
在机器的不同部件间传输数据和信号
between different parts of the machine.
因此它也被称为插线板
For this reason they were also called plug boards.
不过这也意味着
Unfortunately, this meant having to rewire the machine
只要程序改变就必须重新接线
each time a different program needed to be run.
因此到20年代 这些插线板都设计成了可替换的
And so by the 1920s, these plug boards were made swappable.
这不仅让编程更容易了
This not only made programming a lot more comfortable,
也让机器可以载入不同的程序
but also allowed for different programs to be plugged into a machine.
比如 一个板子用于计算营业税
For example, one board might be wired to calculate sales tax,
而另一个用来计算工资总额
while another helps with payroll.
但是用插线板编程实在太复杂了
But plug boards were fiendishly complicated to program.
上面这团乱七八糟的连线是用来计算损益汇总表的
This tangle of wires is a program for calculating a profit loss summary,
用的是IBM 402会计机 它在40年代曾风靡一时
using an IBM 402 accounting machine, which were popular in the 1940s.
插线板这种编程方式对机电式计算机来说也不是孤例
And this style of plug board programming wasn't unique to electromechanical computers.
1946年完工的第一台通用电子计算机ENIAC
The world's first General-Purpose electronic computer, the ENIAC, completed in 1946,
也大量使用了插线板
used a ton of them.
即便在程序在纸上写完之后
Even after a program had been completely figured out on paper,
线缆连接ENIAC并让程序能够运行
physically wiring up the ENIAC and getting the program to run
也可能花费3周以上时间
could take upwards of three weeks.
考虑到这些早期计算机开销之巨
Given the enormous cost of these early computers,
仅仅切换程序就需要宕机数周令人难以接受
weeks of downtime simply to switch programs was unacceptable
因此急需更新 更快 更灵活的编程方式
and the new, faster, more flexible way to programme machines was badly needed.
还好 到40年代末50年代初
Fortunately by the late 1940s and into the 50s,
电子存储出现了
electronic memory was becoming feasible.
随着成本降低 存储容量也在提升
As costs fell, memory size grew.
不再需要通过一堆接线来保存程序了
Instead of storing a program as a physical plug board of wires,
可以直接把程序保存在计算机内存里
it became possible to store a program entirely in a computer's memory,
在内存里程序员可以轻松改变程序 同时CPU也能快速访问它
where it could be easily changed by programmers and quickly accessed by the CPU.
这些计算机称为存储程序计算机
These computers were called stored-program computers.
有了足够大的内存 不仅可以放入待运行的程序
With enough computer memory, you could store not only the program you wanted to run,
还可以把需要的数据也存进去
but also any data your program would need,
甚至包括运行中生成的新数据
including new values it created along the way.
把程序数据统一存储在一起
Unifying the progrmming data into a single shared memory
称为冯诺依曼结构
is called the von Neumann architecture.
它因约翰·冯·诺伊曼得名 他是著名数学家 物理学家
Named after John von Neumann, a prominent mathematician and physicist,
参与了曼哈顿计划和一些早期的电子计算机开发工作
who worked on the Manhattan project and several early electronic computers.
他曾说过 “比起炸弹我在考虑更重要的事情”
and once said, "I'm thinking about something much more important than bombs,
“我在想计算机”
I'm thinking about computers".
冯诺依曼计算机的标志是
The hallmarks of a von Neumann computer
一个处理单元包含ALU
are a processing unit containing an arithmetic logic unit,
数据寄存器 指令寄存器 和指令地址寄存器
data registers, an instruction register, and an instruction address register.
还有 内存同时保存数据和指令
And finally, a memory to store both data and instructions.
希望你还记得
Hopefully, this sounds familiar,
第7期中我们已经完成了一个冯诺依曼计算机、
because we actually built a von Neumann computer in episode 7.
第一台冯诺伊曼结构的存储程序计算机
The very first von Neumann architecture stored program computer
于1948年在曼彻斯特大学建成 小名叫“宝贝”
was constructed in 1948 by the University of Manchester, nicknamed "Baby".
【注：1. Baby是为了试验制造的，又称为Small-Scale Experimental Machine(SSEM,
小规模试验机)，1948.6.21运行了它的第一个程序
2.Baby建成于曼彻斯特维多利亚大学Victoria University of Manchester，是曼大前身】
你现在用的电脑也使用了相同的结构
And even the computer you are watching this video right now uses the same architecture.
现在计算机内存很大
Now electronic computer memory is great and all,
但是要运行程序还是要先加载程序数据
but you still have to load the programming data in to the computer before it can run.
所以当时用了打孔卡
And for this reason, punch cards were used.
看看思想泡泡
Let's get to the Thought Bubble.
直到80年代 几乎所有的计算机都有打孔读卡器
Well into the 1980s, almost all computers had a punch card reader,
它可以每次插入一张卡片
which could suck in a single punch card at a time
并将其内容写入计算机内存
and write the contents of the card into the computer's memory.
如果有一堆打孔卡
If you loaded in a stack of punch cards, the reader would load them all
那么读卡器会依次载入卡片内存
into memory sequentially, as a big block.
只要程序数据进入内存了 计算机会得到通知去执行
Once the programming data were in memory, the computer would be told to execute it.
当然 即便简单的程序也会有上百行指令
Of course, even simple computer programs might have hundreds of instructions,
这意味着程序是保存在一堆打孔卡里的
which meant that programs were stored as stacks of punch cards.
如果你不小心把卡片掉地上了
So if you ever have the misfortune of accidentally dropping your program on the floor,
可能要花数小时乃至数天才能把代码按顺序复原
it could take you hours, days, or even weeks to put the code back in the right order.
一个常用技巧是在卡堆的侧面画一条对角线
A common trick was to draw a diagonal line on the side of the card stack called striping,
这样整理时至少有迹可循
so you'd have at least some clue how to get it back into the right order.
打孔卡记录的最大程序
The largest program ever punched into punch cards
是美国空军的“贤者”防空系统 完成于1955年
was the US Air Force's sage air defense system, completed in 1955.
鼎盛时期 该系统雇佣了全球20%的程序员
At its peak, the product is said to have employed 20% of the world's programmers.
它的主控程序存储于62,500张打孔卡中
Its main control program was stored on a whopping 62,500 punch cards,
大约是5MB的数据量
which is equivalent to roughly 5 megabytes of data.
今天看来稀松平常
Pretty underwhelming by today's standards.
打孔卡不仅可以让计算机载入数据
And punch cards weren't only useful for getting data into computers,
还可以读取计算机的数据
but also getting data out of them.
在程序执行完毕时 可以将结果从内存里写出
At the end of a program, results could be written out of computer memory
通过打孔记录到打孔卡上
and onto punch cards by, well, punching cards.
数据随后可以人工分析
Then this data could be analyzed by humans
或输入到另一台计算机中再次计算
or loaded into a second program for additional computation.
谢谢泡泡
Thanks, Thought Bubble.
与打孔卡类似的是打孔纸带
A close cousin to punch cards was punched paper tape,
它和打孔卡一样 只不过是连续的纸带而不是单张卡片
which is basically the same idea, but continuously instead of being on individual cards.
当然 我们还没谈到硬盘 光驱
And of course, we haven't talked about hard drives, CD-Roms,
DVD U盘以及其他东西
DVDs, USB thumb drives, and other similar goodies.
以后再讲这些高级的存储设备
We'll get to those more advanced types of data storage in a future episode.
最后 在插线板和打孔纸之后
Finally, in addition to plug boards and punch paper,
80年代前出现了另一种普遍的编程和控制计算机的方式
there was another common way to program and control computers
面板编程
pre-1980: panel programming.
它不是通过电缆的物理连接激活相应的功能
Rather than having to physically plug in cables to activate certain functions,
而是在巨大的面板上通过开关和按钮来实现控制
this could also be done with huge panels full of switches and buttons.
也有指示灯
And there were indicator lights to display
显示各功能状态和内存中的数值
the status of various functions and values in memory.
50 60年代的计算机通常都有与此相似的巨大控制台
Computers of the 50s and 60s often featured huge control consoles that look like this.
尽管仅使用开关录入整个程序很少见 但这确实可行的
Although it was rare to input a whole program using just switches, it was possible.
为爱好者设计的早期家用电脑大量使用了开关
And early home computers made for the hobbyist market used switches extensively,
因为他们买不起像打孔卡读卡器这样昂贵的外设
because most home users couldn't afford expensive peripherals like punch card readers.
第一个在商业上取得成功的家用机是Altair 8800
The first commercially successful home computer was the Altair 8800,
【注：Altair 8800是1974年基于Intel 8080所设计的一部微型电脑，当时还在哈佛大学
读书的比尔·盖茨与伙伴保罗·艾伦一起为Altair 8800电脑设计Altair BASIC解译器】
有2种版本：整机和需要组装的散件
which sold in two versions: preassembled and as a kit.
组装散件版受到了业余爱好者的欢迎
The kit, which was popular with amateur computing enthusiasts,
它在1975年以售价史无前例的低价发售 约400美元
sold for the then unprecedented low price of around $400 in 1975
相当于2017年的2000美元
or about $2,000 in 2017.
8800的编程就是拨弄前面板上的开关
To program 8800 you'd literally toggle the switches on the front panel
用来输入指令对应的二进制操作码
to enter the binary opcodes for the instruction you wanted.
然后按下保存按钮把数据写入内存
Then you press the deposit button to write that value into memory.
随后在内存的下一个位置
Then in the next location in memory,
再拨弄开关进入下一个指令 再按保存 以此类推
you toggle the switches again for your next instruction, deposit it and so on.
当把程序全部输入内存后
When you had finally entered your whole program into memory,
拨弄开关 把内存地址复零位
you would toggle the switches, move back to memory address zero,
按下运行按钮 观察指示灯闪烁
press the run button, and watch the little lights blink.
这就是1975年的家用计算机
That was home computing in 1975, wow.
不管是插线板开关还是打孔带
Whether it was plug board switches or punched paper
为早期计算机编程都是专家的差事
programming these early computers was the realm of experts.
要么是专业程序员 要么是技术狂人
Either professionals who did this for a living, or technology enthusiasts.
你需要精通底层硬件
You needed intimate knowledge of the underlying hardware,
比如处理器的操作码以及寄存器位宽才能写出程序
so as things like processor opcodes and register width to write programs.
这样的编程既困难又无趣
This meant programming was hard and tedious.
甚至连专业工程师和科学家使用时
And even professional engineers and scientists struggle
也是捉襟见肘
to take full advantage of what computing could offer.
需要更简单的方式指示电脑工作
What was needed was a simpler way to tell computers what to do;
一个更容易写程序的方法
a simpler way to write programs.
这正是下期要讲的编程语言
And that brings us to programming languages which we'll talk about next episode.
下周见
See you next week.
阿尔法小分队荣誉译制
翻：@Auriance  校：@ErrorEnvyEnchant 压制：@Mihael_Ho
长期招募 详情见微博置顶@阿尔法小分队科教组